<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>OSINT News</title>
    <link href="https://osint-news.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://osint-news.github.io" />
    <updated>2023-02-18T13:50:48+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Badger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://osint-news.github.io</id>

    <entry>
        <title>The Seint&#x27;s Christmas CTF — Part 3</title>
        <author>
            <name>Badger</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://osint-news.github.io/the-seints-christmas-ctf-part-3.html"/>
        <id>https://osint-news.github.io/the-seints-christmas-ctf-part-3.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/blinded-by-the-lights.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="CTF"/>

        <updated>2023-02-18T13:50:48+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/blinded-by-the-lights.jpg" alt="" />
                    Blinded by the Lights! I fell into a bit of a rabbit-hole on Part 3 of The Seint’s CTF, as you’ll see. It’s an example of confirmation bias, which can be a problem with any investigation. The key takeaway is to trust The Seint! If&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/blinded-by-the-lights.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <h3 id="blinded-by-the-lights">Blinded by the Lights!</h3>
<p>I fell into a bit of a rabbit-hole on Part 3 of The Seint’s CTF, as you’ll see. It’s an example of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confirmation_bias"><em>confirmation bias</em></a>, which can be a problem with any investigation. The key takeaway is to <strong>trust The Seint</strong>!</p>
<p><em>If you want to go back to the beginning of this walkthrough, you can find it <a href="https://osint-news.github.io/osint-walkthrough-the-seint-ctf-2022.html">here</a>. <strong>Spoilers ahead!</strong></em></p>
<p>One upside of falling down the rabbit hole is that it gave me a chance to play with ChatGPT, which is clearly going to be a key ingredient in OSINT work in future, if only for the speed-up it gives you with coding. More on that later, but first let’s take a look at the clue:</p>
<pre><code>The next message came on the first day of August. It said: &quot;I know you found the cloth in Brno. The colour reminded me of a song and a movie from 1984 that had the same title. I remembered there was a place named just like the song and wanted to find it while being in Paris. I found the place on the map, but the shop wasn&#39;t there. People said it moved some time ago. I came to the nearest intersection and tried to look left first, but the sun was shining right into my eyes, just along the street. What was the time?&quot;

The exact time in HH:MM format turned into a hash is the password to the next message. The time must be in that place&#39;s timezone.
</code></pre>
<p>As a long time Prince fan, I had no problem with the shop. I just opened up Google Maps in Paris, and searched for “Purple Rain”:
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/06-purple-rain.jpg" alt="Purple Rain, in Paris" width="955" height="544"  sizes="100vw" srcset="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/06-purple-rain-xs.jpg 300w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/06-purple-rain-sm.jpg 480w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/06-purple-rain-md.jpg 768w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/06-purple-rain-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/06-purple-rain-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/06-purple-rain-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></p>
<p>However, this is when I fell down the rabbit hole, jumping into Street View when there was no need. I walked up to the nearest intersection and saw that the most recent image was from May 2022. That persuaded me that The Seint couldn’t have been talking about 1 August 2022, and I would need to jump into the timeline…</p>
<p>Sure enough, the sun was shining right into the Google camera in August <strong>2020</strong>:
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/07-blinded.jpg" alt="View of street in Paris, sun shining directly into camera." width="1279" height="743"  sizes="100vw" srcset="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/07-blinded-xs.jpg 300w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/07-blinded-sm.jpg 480w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/07-blinded-md.jpg 768w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/07-blinded-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/07-blinded-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/07-blinded-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></p>
<p>Of course, part of my brain said “that’s <strong>not</strong> looking left from the intersection, it’s looking right back”, but I managed to convince myself I was right, and fired up <a href="https://www.suncalc.org/#/48.8731,2.3451,18/2020.08.01/10:24/1/3">SunCalc</a>, looking in <em>completely the wrong direction</em>, on <em>completely the wrong date</em>, but somehow still  convinced that I was right!
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/08-suncalc-1.jpg" alt="SunCalc simulation of sun in Paris on 01/08/2020" width="1100" height="564"  sizes="100vw" srcset="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/08-suncalc-1-xs.jpg 300w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/08-suncalc-1-sm.jpg 480w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/08-suncalc-1-md.jpg 768w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/08-suncalc-1-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/08-suncalc-1-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/08-suncalc-1-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></p>
<p>This gave me a time of around 10:24 local. I hashed that, and a couple of minutes each way, and tried entering those hashes into the Zip for the next level. Nada. I then tried a few more minutes each way. Still nothing. I went back to StreetView and looked for any other indications of the time, and came away scratching my head. I wasn’t going to spend the rest of the day hashing random times, so I decided to fire up Python and ChatGPT. Thanks to Advent of Code, I’m already familiar with <code>hashlib</code>, but I potentially wanted to generate a lot of hashes. I simply asked ChatGPT to write a loop to format times from 09:00 to 11:30 in the format “hh:mm” and hash them all. It took ChatGPT about five seconds to write this:
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/09-code-1.jpg" alt="Python code to hash formatted times" width="1360" height="1298"  sizes="100vw" srcset="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/09-code-1-xs.jpg 300w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/09-code-1-sm.jpg 480w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/09-code-1-md.jpg 768w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/09-code-1-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/09-code-1-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/09-code-1-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></p>
<p>Of course, this resulted in 150 hashes, and there was no way I was going to try and apply them by hand…
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/10-chatgpt.jpg" alt="ChatGPT conversation" width="758" height="641"  sizes="100vw" srcset="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/10-chatgpt-xs.jpg 300w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/10-chatgpt-sm.jpg 480w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/10-chatgpt-md.jpg 768w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/10-chatgpt-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/10-chatgpt-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/10-chatgpt-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></p>
<p>With the information about exception handling, which I already know about, I soon had a loop that tried all 150 hashes against the Zip for Part 4. Still nothing! 🤬</p>
<p>At this point, since I basically now had a tool that could brute force the answer, I decided to widen the parameters, find the correct time, and then try to figure out where I went wrong. The correct time turned out to be a fair bit later in the day: 14:17.</p>
<p>Back to SunCalc, and moving the clock forward to the right time made me realise I should have been listening to my doubts:
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/11-suncalc-2.jpg" alt="SunCalc simulation of sun in Paris on 01/08/2020" width="1081" height="589"  sizes="100vw" srcset="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/11-suncalc-2-xs.jpg 300w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/11-suncalc-2-sm.jpg 480w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/11-suncalc-2-md.jpg 768w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/11-suncalc-2-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/11-suncalc-2-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/3/responsive/11-suncalc-2-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></p>
<p>Of course, <strong>this is looking left</strong> from the intersection, just as The Seint said. But the sun isn’t completely lined up… Eventually the penny dropped that if The Seint was right about the direction, maybe I need to think again about the date. It is the 2022 puzzle after all, and I only ended up looking at 2020 for spurious reasons. Sure enough, on 01/08/2022, at 14:17, <a href="https://www.suncalc.org/#/48.8731,2.3451,18/2022.08.01/14:17/1/3">the sun lines up beautifully</a>.</p>
<p>Finally, then, with a painful reminder that <em>confirmation bias</em> is always a consideration when conducting OSINT or any kind of investigation, it was off to Part 4!</p>
<hr>
<p><em>Feature photo is a crop of an original by <a href="https://www.pexels.com/photo/the-louvre-pyramid-in-france-during-the-golden-hour-11783046/">Mathias Reding @ Pexels</a></em></p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Seint&#x27;s Christmas CTF — Part 2</title>
        <author>
            <name>Badger</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://osint-news.github.io/the-seints-christmas-ctf-part-2.html"/>
        <id>https://osint-news.github.io/the-seints-christmas-ctf-part-2.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/eirik-solheim-mWTOR3Rx8l8-unsplash.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="CTF"/>

        <updated>2023-02-18T13:42:50+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/eirik-solheim-mWTOR3Rx8l8-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />
                    If you want to see Part 1 of this walkthrough, you can find it here. Spoilers ahead! Part 2 of The Seint’s challenge would have been a real head-scratcher for me if it hadn’t appeared in a puzzle before. Here’s the text in step2.txt: The&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/eirik-solheim-mWTOR3Rx8l8-unsplash.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><em>If you want to see Part 1 of this walkthrough, you can find it <a href="https://osint-news.github.io/osint-walkthrough-the-seint-ctf-2022.html">here</a>. <strong>Spoilers ahead!</strong></em></p>
<p>Part 2 of The Seint’s challenge would have been a real head-scratcher for me if it hadn’t appeared in a puzzle before. Here’s the text in <code>step2.txt</code>:</p>
<pre><code>The next message I got from my friend was strange. I think there was something wrong with her phone. The message I got was just &quot;Going to 727774447777&quot;. Did she want to type a phone number or something was wrong with her phone? Could that be the hint to find the clue to her next location? 

The place she was travelling to (lowercase -&gt; hash) is the password.
</code></pre>
<p>That doesn’t look like any phone number I’ve ever seen, but the mention of a phone is a big hint! Unfortunately, many of The Seint’s readers may not be old enough to remember phones that looked like this:
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/04-Nokia-3310-wikipedia.png" alt="Nokia 3310" width="400" height="912"  sizes="100vw" srcset="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/responsive/04-Nokia-3310-wikipedia-xs.png 300w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/responsive/04-Nokia-3310-wikipedia-sm.png 480w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/responsive/04-Nokia-3310-wikipedia-md.png 768w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/responsive/04-Nokia-3310-wikipedia-lg.png 1024w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/responsive/04-Nokia-3310-wikipedia-xl.png 1360w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/responsive/04-Nokia-3310-wikipedia-2xl.png 1600w"></figure></p>
<p>(<em>I used to tweet with a phone like this!</em>)</p>
<p>When sending SMS, or writing contact names, we used to have to tap a number key repeatedly to get the right letter. For example, tapping ‘7’ once gave us ‘P’, but tapping it three times gave us ‘R’. With that information, it should be easy to work out what the numbers represent, and we can get our MD5 hash.</p>
<h4 id="the-multi-tap-phone-cipher">The Multi-tap Phone Cipher</h4>
<p>If you ever get a longer string of numbers to decrypt, you might want to automate things. There is no Operation in CyberChef for this type of cipher, but luckily CyberChef isn’t the only game in town, and we can use the French <a href="https://www.dcode.fr/multitap-abc-cipher">dCode</a> site, which has such a decoder (<em>and encoder in case you ever want to set your own fun puzzles</em>).
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/05-dcode.jpg" alt="Screenshot of dcode.fr" width="1008" height="507"  sizes="100vw" srcset="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/responsive/05-dcode-xs.jpg 300w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/responsive/05-dcode-sm.jpg 480w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/responsive/05-dcode-md.jpg 768w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/responsive/05-dcode-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/responsive/05-dcode-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/2/responsive/05-dcode-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></p>
<p>And with that, we’re <a href="https://osint-news.github.io/the-seints-christmas-ctf-part-3.html">off to Part 3</a>!</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>OSINT Walkthrough - The Seint&#x27;s Christmas CTF, 2022</title>
        <author>
            <name>Badger</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://osint-news.github.io/osint-walkthrough-the-seint-ctf-2022.html"/>
        <id>https://osint-news.github.io/osint-walkthrough-the-seint-ctf-2022.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/pexels-ignat-arapov-6638877.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="CTF"/>

        <updated>2023-02-18T13:42:18+00:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/pexels-ignat-arapov-6638877.jpg" alt="" />
                    I am a bit late to The Seint’s now annual OSINT CTF, but that’s probably a good thing as this series will contain spoilers. You can follow along in the posts ahead, or you can always have a go yourself at this repo. You will&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/pexels-ignat-arapov-6638877.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>I am a bit late to The Seint’s now annual OSINT CTF, but that’s probably a good thing as this series will contain spoilers. You can follow along in the posts ahead, or you can always have a go yourself <a href="https://github.com/seintpl/osintquiz/tree/main/2022">at this repo</a>. You will also find the 2021 CTF on GitHub.</p>
<p>Rather than provide a simple show-and-tell, I will also try to share any learning I picked up along the way. This assumes I even complete the challenge, of course!</p>
<p>We start off with a password-protected Zip file (<em>2022.zip</em>), which contains all the puzzles nested inside each other. The password to the next step is always the MD5 hash made of the current step’s answer written in lower case.</p>
<p><strong>Care! Please don’t open random Zip files downloaded from the internet without testing them! There’s no reason to be distrustful of The Seint, but good file hygiene should be standard practice.</strong></p>
<p>We’re told that the first password, to get us going, is the MD5 hash of the word “summer” (without quotes), so let’s head off to <a href="https://cyberchef.org/">CyberChef</a>.</p>
<h3 id="spoiler-warning">Spoiler Warning</h3>
<p>This is a walkthrough, so you will find spoilers below and in the subsequent posts in this series. Do try and solve the puzzles on your own before reading ahead!</p>
<h3 id="creating-an-md5-hash-in-cyberchef">Creating an MD5 Hash in CyberChef</h3>
<p>If you’ve never used CyberChef before, it can be a bit intimidating, but it’s really very straightforward. There are <strong>operations</strong> on the left, which can be combined in order to create a <strong>recipe</strong> in the centre (you can simply drag the operations over). The recipe takes one ingredient (<strong>Input</strong>, top right), and hopefully bakes a nice <strong>Output</strong> (bottom right). There are lots of operations you can perform in CyberChef, but we’re only interested in one for now.</p>
<p>Using either the Search function or by browsing in the section titled Hashing, find <strong>MD5</strong> and drag it into the recipe. Type “summer” in the Input field and watch the hash magically appear in the Output field:
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/01-cyberchef.jpg" alt="Screenshot of CyberChef" width="961" height="577"  sizes="100vw" srcset="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/01-cyberchef-xs.jpg 300w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/01-cyberchef-sm.jpg 480w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/01-cyberchef-md.jpg 768w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/01-cyberchef-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/01-cyberchef-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/01-cyberchef-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></p>
<p>You can now unzip the archive and see what files we’ve got for Stage 1:</p>
<pre><code>step1.txt
step1 - hint 1.txt
step1 - hint 2.txt
step2.zip
</code></pre>
<p>Try and avoid the hints if you possibly can; they’re there for if you really get stuck!</p>
<p>Last year, The Seint started us off fairly gently, so let’s see if we’re getting the same treatment this year. Here’s <code>step1.txt</code>:</p>
<pre><code>This summer, I got a message from my friend. I knew she was planning to visit Europe, but didn&#39;t have any clue where she was going. The message said: &quot;I came to a city that welcomed me with a puzzle. While sightseeing I was tricked to go to the train station an hour earlier. And that&#39;s all because of the cathedral bells ringing noon not at the time you&#39;d expect them to. While I ran down from the hill along a little street named after a president, just behind that cathedral I noticed a skull painted by a gate. Just behing that gate somebody left a piece of cloth. Its color is the password that will let you find my next exact location.&quot;

Make a hash of the color name to uncover the next step.
</code></pre>
<p>This is a really good scenario for highlighting something The Seint says in the introduction to this CTF: <em><strong>Remember that the tools aren’t enough. Use your open mind and try not to fall in the mind traps.</strong></em></p>
<p>It’s tempting to rely on tools in the OSINT world, but occasionally you just have to charm Google or Bing with the right search term (<em>much like we’re all learning how to craft prompts to get the most out of our new AI tools</em>). So let’s try and find a European city whose cathedral bells ring noon an hour early. It took several iterations before I found the answer with:
<code>&quot;europe cathedral ringing noon at 11&quot;</code></p>
<p>Which led to a promising result:
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/02-brno.jpg" alt="Google search results" width="627" height="127"  sizes="100vw" srcset="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/02-brno-xs.jpg 300w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/02-brno-sm.jpg 480w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/02-brno-md.jpg 768w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/02-brno-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/02-brno-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/02-brno-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></p>
<p>The ‘little street named after a president’ turns out to be too little to find on an overhead view in Google Maps, so I ended up doing what I often do in CTFs, which is simply to have a good hunt around ‘on foot’, i.e., in Street View. Eventually, I found the skull on an alley named after the first president of the Czech Repulic:
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/03-skull.jpg" alt="Image of alley behind Brno Cathedral. Source: Google Maps" width="977" height="551"  sizes="100vw" srcset="https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/03-skull-xs.jpg 300w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/03-skull-sm.jpg 480w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/03-skull-md.jpg 768w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/03-skull-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/03-skull-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://osint-news.github.io/media/posts/1/responsive/03-skull-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></p>
<p>True enough, on the other side of that gate is a large piece of cloth in a fairly distinctive colour. (<em>The relevant image was taken in 2017, so if it’s replaced with a more recent image before you try this CTF, you might need to use the Street View Timeline to go back to 2017</em>) Hashing the cloth’s colour allows us to open <code>step2.zip</code>, and you can see how I get on with that step in the <a href="https://osint-news.github.io/the-seints-christmas-ctf-part-2.html">next post</a>!</p>
<h6 id="im-stuck">I’m stuck!</h6>
<p>If you can’t find the gate by plodding around Brno cathedral, you’re welcome to click on the spoiler below. This will take you to the location of the gate in Google Maps, and you should be able to find the cloth fairly easily.</p>
<p><details>
    <summary><strong>Spoiler</strong></summary>
    <a href="https://www.google.co.uk/maps/@49.1912386,16.6081611,3a,75y,166.93h,98.71t/data=!3m6!1e1!3m4!1sWnBnK_ZUr2um8CfmkEunKA!2e0!7i13312!8i6656">Google Maps</a>
</details></p>

<h6 id="takeaway">Takeaway</h6>
<p>Sometimes, there’s no substitute for simply spending a bit of time trying lots of variations of search terms (and search engines), or wandering around aimlessly in Google Street View. There aren’t always magic shortcuts in OSINT, despite whatever tools come along!</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
